Student Publications; Collection ua805
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Student Publications Collection
1943-1993
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
State University of New York at Albany--Students
ua805
2.59 cubic ft.
Collection is made up of publications from students of the University at Albany, the vast majority of them publishing prose and poetry, as well as artwork created by students.
Historical Note
Student published materials are mainstay of university life, typically serving as artistic outlets for students who wish to display their creations related to their field of study. The University at Albany has had many various examples of this throughout its history. The majority of these publications were released in the 1960s and 1970s, though some like the "State Lion" and "The Primer" originated earlier.
Many publications at the university helped promote prose and poetry written by students, such as the "State Lion" and "Tangent." Others tried to focus their interest on visual art created by students. For example "Observation" took work from all visual mediums that could be printed on the page and published them for all to see. Still others would accept all artistic mediums, such as "Phoenix," which would publish stories written by students, as well as art and photographs from students. Sometimes they would be combined, with photographs being used in conjunction with a piece of prose or poetry to visualize the written material.
The last publication was a separate yearbook for a single residence hall. For two years the residents of Sayles Hall published their own yearbooks using their own materials with some assistance form the faculty and staff in building the book itself. It featured residents of the dorm and the events that occurred their during the year using photographs taken by the students.
Scope and Contents
This collections contains various publications, the majority dating to the 1960s and 1970s. The first one is the State Lion which was a literary magazine published by the Student Association from 1936-1935. Like the other publications, it consisted solely of student work. The second publication is the "Observation" which was a collection of visual artwork by student, and published from 1966-1973. Mediums included within the publication ranged from paintings and sketches to photographs. "Parsec" was another literary magazine that focused on works of science fiction written by students. The collection contains copies from 1969 and from 1972-1975. Another publication called "Phoenix" combined student prose and poetry, with visual arts, publishing work done in both fields. In our collection are various editions from 1971-1977. "The Primer" was another student published literary magazine. It included a variety of prose and poetry and this collection consists of copies published from 1943-1970.
The Tangent was another literary magazine that combined the literary and visual arts, using student art to represent images within the prose and poetry. This collection has two copies from 1981 and 1982. "The Word," another literary magazine, would combine the typical work submitted by students with review of mainstream literature. This was published solely by students from 1967-1968. The final literary magazine was the Statesman which was published from 1939-1941. Like the others in consisted mostly of short stories and poetry written by students. Marcia Brown was the editor-in-chief of the magazine for the first three issues. The final part of this collection is the Sayles Hall Yearbook. This was a publication from the residents of Sayles Hall from 1992-1993, and acted as their personal yearbook for all people and events related to the dorm. They have a scrapbook feel, since many of there pages include photographs taken by the students throughout the year, and combined in to collages.
Arrangement of the Collection
Collection is broken down by publication, and arranged chronologically within those groups.
Acquisition Information
All items in this collection were transferred to the University Libraries, M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives.
Related Materials
Related collections in the M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives can be found in the subject guide for Criminal Justice and Prisons.
Access
Access to this collection is unrestricted.
Student publications; College student newspapers and periodicals; College students' writings, American--20th century; College student's art; UAlbany Student Groups
- Observation, 1966-1973; 1; 0.2 cubic ft.
  Arrangement
  Materials are arranged chronologically.
  Scope and Contents
  Collection is made up of the student art publication Observation.
  - Observation, 1966 (Box 1 (1-Observation), Volume 1)
  - Observation, 1968 (Box 1 (1-Observation), Volume 2)
  - Observation, 1969 (Box 1 (1-Observation), Volume 3)
  - Observation, 1970 (Box 1 (1-Observation), Volume 4)
  - Observation, 1971 (Box 1 (1-Observation), Volume 5)
  - Observation, 1972 (Box 1 (1-Observation), Volume 6)
  - Observation, 1973 (Box 1 (1-Observation), Volume 7)
- Memo From Minnie, 1962-1967; 0.085 cubic ft.
  Files in this series are arranged chronologically.
  This series contains copies of the Memo From Minnie, a handbook for women students produced by the Association of Women Students.
  - Memo From Minnie, 1962 (Box 1 (2-Parsec))
  - Memo From Minnie, 1963-1964 (Box 1 (2-Parsec))
  - "From Minnie" Draft, 1964 (Box 1 (2-Parsec))
  - Memo From Minnie, 1964-1965 (Box 1 (2-Parsec))
  - Memo From Minnie, 1965-1966 (Box 1 (2-Parsec))
  - Memo From Minnie, 1966-1967 (Box 1 (2-Parsec))
- Parsec, 1969-1975; 2; 0.085 cubic ft.
  Collection is made up of the student science ficiton publication "Parsec."
  - Parsec, 1969 (Box 1 (2-Parsec), Volume 1)
  - Parsec, 1972 (Box 1 (2-Parsec), Volume 2)
  - Parsec, 1973 (Box 1 (2-Parsec), Volume 3)
  - Parsec, 1974 (Box 1 (2-Parsec), Volume 4)
  - Parsec, 1975 (Box 1 (2-Parsec), Volume 5)
- Phoenix, 1971-1977; 3; 0.2 cubic ft.
  Collection is made up of the student literary publication Phoenix.
  - Phoenix Volume 1 Number 1, ca. 1971 (Box 1 (3-Phoenix), Folder 1)
  - Phoenix Volume 2 Number 2, 1972 February (Box 1 (3-Phoenix), Folder 2)
  - Phoenix Volume 2 Number 3, 1972 May (Box 1 (3-Phoenix), Folder 3)
  - Phoenix Volume 2 Number 4, 1972 May (Box 1 (3-Phoenix), Folder 4)
  - Phoenix Volume 3 Number 1, 1972 November (Box 1 (3-Phoenix), Folder 5)
  - Phoenix Volume 3 Number 2, 1973 April (Box 1 (3-Phoenix), Folder 6)
  - Phoenix Volume 5 Number 1, 1974 October (Box 1 (3-Phoenix), Folder 7)
  - Phoenix Volume 5 Number 2, 1975 April (Box 1 (3-Phoenix), Folder 8)
  - Phoenix Volume 6 Number 2, 1976 April (Box 1 (3-Phoenix), Folder 9)
  - Phoenix Volume 7 Number 1, 1976 October (Box 1 (3-Phoenix), Folder 10)
  - Phoenix Volume 7 Number 2, 1977 April (Box 1 (3-Phoenix), Folder 11)
  - Phoenix Volume 8 Number 1, 1977 October (Box 1 (3-Phoenix), Folder 12)
- Primer, 1943-1970; 4; 0.68 cubic ft.
  - The Primer, 1943 May (Volume 1)
  - The Primer, ca. 1944 (Volume 1)
  - The Primer, 1945 May (Volume 1)
  - The Primer, 1946 (Volume 1)
  - The Primer, 1947 (Volume 1)
  - The Primer, 1947 December (Volume 2)
  - The Primer, 1948 April (Volume 2)
  - The Primer, 1949 (Volume 2)
  - The Primer, 1950 (Volume 2)
  - The Primer, 1951 (Volume 2)
  - The Primer, 1952 (Volume 2)
  - The Primer, 1953 (Volume 3)
  - The Primer, 1954 (Volume 3)
  - The Primer, 1955 (Volume 3)
  - The Primer, 1956 (Volume 3)
  - The Primer, 1957 (Volume 3)
  - The Primer, 1958 (Volume 4)
  - The Primer, 1959 (Volume 4)
  - The Primer, 1960 (Volume 4)
  - The Primer, 1961 (Volume 4)
  - The Primer, Undated (Volume 5)
  - The Primer, 1962 Janaury (Volume 5)
  - The Primer, 1963 April (Volume 5)
  - The Primer, 1964 April (Volume 5)
  - The Primer, 1965 (Volume 6)
  - The Primer, 1965 October (Volume 6)
  - The Primer, 1966 April (Volume 6)
  - The Primer, 1966 October (Volume 6)
  - The Primer, 1967 April (Volume 6)
  - The Primer, 1968 (Box 1 (4-Primer))
  - The Primer, 1968 October (Box 1 (4-Primer))
  - The Primer, 1969 January (Box 1 (4-Primer))
  - The Primer, 1969 April (Box 1 (4-Primer))
  - The Primer, 1970 January (Box 1 (4-Primer))
  - The Primer, 1970 April (Box 1 (4-Primer))
  - Primer Report of Activities of the Year 1947-1948 (Box 1 (4-Primer))
- Sayles Hall Yearbook, 1992-1993; 5; 0.17 cubic ft.
  - Sayles Hall Yearbook, 1992 (Volume 1)
  - Sayles Hall Yearbook, 1993 (Volume 2)
- State Lion, 1926-1939; 6; 0.66 cubic ft.
  - State Lione Volume 1 Number 1, 1926 December (Volume 1)
  - State Lione Volume 1 Number 2, 1927 April (Volume 1)
  - State Lione Volume 2 Number 1, 1927 October (Volume 1)
  - State Lione Volume 2 Number 2, 1927 December (Volume 1)
  - State Lione Volume 2 Number 3, 1928 March (Volume 1)
  - State Lione Volume 2 Number 4, 1928 June (Volume 1)
  - State Lione Volume 3 Number 1, 1928 September (Volume 2)
  - State Lione Volume 3 Number 2, 1928 October (Volume 2)
  - State Lione Volume 3 Number 3, 1928 December (Volume 2)
  - State Lione Volume 3 Number 4, 1929 February (Volume 2)
  - State Lione Volume 3 Number 5, 1929 April (Volume 2)
  - State Lione Volume 4 Number 1, 1929 June (Volume 2)
  - State Lione Volume 5 Number 1, 1929 October (Volume 3)
  - State Lione Volume 5 Number 2, 1929 November (Volume 3)
  - State Lione Volume 5 Number 3, 1929 December (Volume 3)
  - State Lione Volume 5 Number 4, 1930 March (Volume 3)
  - State Lione Volume 5 Number 5, 1930 April (Volume 3)
  - State Lione Volume 5 Number 6, 1930 April (Volume 3)
  - State Lione Volume 6 Number 1, 1930 September (Volume 4)
  - State Lione Volume 6 Number 2, 1930 November (Volume 4)
  - State Lione Volume 6 Number 3, 1930 December (Volume 4)
  - State Lione Volume 6 Number 4, 1931 February (Volume 4)
  - State Lione Volume 7 Number 5, 1931 April (Volume 4)
  - State Lione Volume 7 Number 6, 1931 June (Volume 4)
  - State Lione Volume 8 Number 1, 1931 September (Volume 5)
  - State Lione Volume 8 Number 2, 1931 November (Volume 5)
  - State Lione Volume 8 Number 3, 1931 December (Volume 5)
  - State Lione Volume 8 Number 4, 1932 February (Volume 5)
  - State Lione Volume 9 Number 1, 1932 November (Volume 5)
  - State Lione Volume 9 Number 2, 1932 December (Volume 5)
  - State Lione Volume 10 Number 1, 1933 November (Volume 6)
  - State Lione Volume 10 Number 2, 1934 April (Volume 6)
  - State Lione Volume 11 Number 1, 1934 October (Volume 6)
  - State Lione Volume 11 Number 2, 1935 January (Volume 6)
  - State Lione Volume 11 Number 3, 1935 April (Volume 6)
  - State Lione Volume 12 Number 1, 1935 October (Volume 7)
  - State Lione Volume 12 Number 2, 1936 January (Volume 7)
  - State Lione Volume 12 Number 3, 1936 April (Volume 7)
  - State Lione Volume 12 Number 4, 1936 June (Volume 7)
  - State Lione Volume 13 Number 1, 1936 October (Volume 7)
  - State Lione Volume 13 Number 2, 1937 January (Volume 7)
  - State Lione Volume 13 Number 3, 1937 April (Volume 7)
  - State Lione Volume 13 Number 4, 1937 June (Volume 7)
  - State Lione Volume 14 Number 1, 1937 October (Volume 8)
  - State Lione Volume 14 Number 2, 1938 January (Volume 8)
  - State Lione Volume 14 Number 3, 1938 April (Volume 8)
  - State Lione Volume 14 Number 4, 1938 June (Volume 8)
  - State Lione Volume 15 Number 1, 1938 October (Volume 8)
  - State Lione Volume 15 Number 2, 1939 January (Volume 8)
  - State Lione Volume 15 Number 3, 1939 April (Volume 8)
  - State Lione Volume 15 Number 4, 1939 June (Volume 8)
- Statesman, 1939 November-1942 April; 7; 0.17 cubic ft.
  - Statesman Volume 1 Number 1, 1939 November (Volume 1)
  - Statesman Volume 1 Number 2, 1940 March (Volume 1)
  - Statesman Volume 1 Number 3, 1940 April (Volume 1)
  - Statesman Volume 1 Number 4, 1940 June (Volume 1)
  - Statesman Volume 2 Number 1, 1940 November (Volume 1)
  - Statesman Volume 2 Number 2, 1941 February (Volume 1)
  - Statesman Volume 2 Number 3, 1941 April (Volume 1)
  - Statesman Volume 2 Number 4, 1941 April (Volume 1)
  - Statesman Volume 3 Number 1, 1941 November (Volume 2)
  - Statesman Volume 3 Number 2, 1942 February (Volume 2)
  - Statesman Volume 3 Number 3, 1942 April (Volume 2)
- Tangent, 1981-1982; 8; 0.17 cubic ft.
  - Tangent, 1981 (Box 1 (8-Tangent), Folder 1)
  - Tangent, 1982 (Box 1 (8-Tangent), Folder 1)
- The Word, 1967 March-1968 October; 9; 0.17 cubic ft.
  - The Word Volume 1 Number 1, 1967 March (Box 1 (9-The Word), Folder 1)
  - The Word Volume 2 Number 1, 1967 November (Box 1 (9-The Word), Folder 1)
  - The Word Volume 2 Number 2, 1968 February (Box 1 (9-The Word), Folder 1)
  - The Word Volume 2 Number 3, 1968 May (Box 1 (9-The Word), Folder 1)
  - The Word Volume 3 Number 1, 1968 Ocotber (Box 1 (9-The Word), Folder 1)
  - The Word, Undated (Box 1 (9-The Word), Folder 1)